Carlos Colmenares A.

Miranda State. Venezuela



ccolmenaresa@gmail.com



+58 0414 3246396



linkedin.com/in/zcoder

Summary

I have a bachelor's degree in Electronic engineering, although I have always worked as a software engineer.

I have worked as an IBM Mainframe specialist, being a systems programmer for two banks, I have also been the software director of a North American software development company with a global presence, and I have also had a successful career as a project engineer, mainly designing and installing electronic security systems for public safety and microwave telecommunications.

I have been a consultant for the development of complex projects in more than forty (40) national and foreign corporations, some of which are as prestigious as Registro Nacional de Costa Rica (San José, Costa Rica), Banco Invercredito (Bogotá, Colombia), PDVSA, Cargill, CANTV, CVG, Metro de Caracas, as well as thirteen (13) banks in Venezuela.

My greatest passion has always been software programming, and as a freelancer, I develop websites, smartphones, and server applications. This passion forces me to stay constantly updated on new technologies and trends within the software development ecosystem (Python, Javascript, HTML, CSS, NodeJS, MySQL, MongoDB, APIs, and Artificial Intelligence...).

I am available to provide my professional services to a company that needs to develop or consolidate its presence in Latin America or anywhere else in the world, either in person or remotely.

Experience



Senior Consultant

Self-employed

Jul 2019 - Present (4 years)

During and after the covid pandemic, I had to reinvent myself.

Goal:

Since then I starting to develop applications for smartphones, PCs, and cloud/desktop servers.

In another way, continue to provide consulting, and maintenance services for those legacy telecommunications and electronic security projects.

Stack:

(by technologies and manufacturers)

*Electronic security systems:

Rosslare, Chiyu, Lenel, Dashou, Dahua, Hikvision.

*Telecommunications:

Ubiquiti, MikroTik, M® Canopy, Cambium Network, VideoComm, Airlive, Trango.

*Web software development:

HTML, CSS, Javascript, React, NodeJS, Python, MySQL, MongoDB, Figma, Git, APIs, etc.

*IBM's Mainframe technologies:

VSE/ESA, VM/ESA, MVS/ESA, OS/390, z/OS. Assembler, VTAM, NCP, CICS, SNA, SDLC, VSAM, JCL, Cobol, JES2, TSO, ACF/POWER, ACF/ICCF, ICKDSF, DB2, DITTO, CA-Vollie, CA-Roscoe, etc.

Senior Project Engineer

CYCS Ingeniería e Instalaciones

Feb 2012 - Jun 2019 (7 years 5 months)

I'm in charge to develop the consulting management area.

Goal:

Design, installation, and training services for network systems, and industrial-grade electronic security systems.

Results:

The success of my management is endorsed, both by the quantity and the technical complexity of the projects successfully executed for large-scale corporate clients.

Projects:

1. Sisven de Venezuela - 1 year

The team leader of installs +1000 cameras of CCTV.

2. Connectix Distribuidora - 2 years

The team leader of installs a lot of surveillance and access control project deployments on its customers.

3. Consultores Cibernéticos - 3 years

The team leader of installs a lot of surveillance and access control project deployments on its customers.

4. ABA tower (Offices Building) - 7 years

Project engineer for all surveillance and A/C systems projects deployments.

5. Los Tulipanes Multi-dwelling building - 6 months

Project engineer to install 64 cameras based on the IP Dahua system.

6. MINCI - 1 year

Project engineer to install 256 cameras based on the IP Hikvision system.

7. FITVEN 2013 - 2 months

Project engineer to install a high-level surveillance system (composed of 48 IP cameras) running on a microwave video network for transmission, based on Airlive technologies.

8. DESCA - 1 year

Project engineer to all surveillance and A/C systems projects deployments on its customers.

9. CARGILL de Venezuela (USA) - 1 year

Project engineer to install a complex A/C system (based on Chiyu technologies), in each of its sixteen (16) industrial factories across the country.

10. Industrias CEGASA - 3 years

Project engineer to install a complex IP surveillance system running on a microwave video network for transmission, based on Airlive technologies and an A/C system (based on Chiyu technologies); all in its big factory.

11. TORREON tower (Offices Building) - 3 years

Project engineer for all surveillance and A/C systems projects deployments.

Senior Project Engineer

CYCS Computing Specialists

Sep 1991 - Dec 2011 (20 years 4 months)

I'm in charge to develop the consulting management area.

Goal:

- 1) Capitalize on the highly technical requirements of those clients with IT infrastructure based solely on IBM Mainframe technologies
- 2) Design and installation of Microwave Telecommunications Networks and Industrial-grade Electronic Security Systems.

Results:

The success of my management is endorsed by the extensive hiring of clients for the development of high-level technical projects.

Projects:

1. Instituto Vialidad Estado Vargas - 1 year

Telephony system implementation based on a wireless platform to provide access to PSTN

2. Banco Hipotecario Latinoamericana - 6 months

Design and install a wireless platform to provide Internet access backhaul to its branches

3. Guardia Nacional de Venezuela - 2 years

The TETRA telecommunication platform reengineering

4. Apostadero Naval de Turiamo - 6 months

Design an IP wireless link to connect two military bases and share broadband internet access between them

5. Policía Municipal Estado Vargas - 1 year

Telephony system implementation based on a wireless platform to provide access to PSTN

6. DIEX - 4 years

Design the telecommunication platform to connect all branches with headquarter

7. C-COM de Venezuela (ISP) - 1-year

Motorola's links using canopy radios installation project for its client Microstar

8. Banco Fondo Común - 3 months

Design and installation of a DPL link to connect to another business partner bank

9. Comsat de Venezuela (ISP) - 6 months

VSAT links installation project for its client Miranda EAP

10. Banco Interbank - 4 years

IBM's VM & VSE/ESA operating system technologies project engineering and consulting services

11. Banco Mi Casa EAP - 6 months

IBM's AS/400 infrastructure & software technologies project engineering and consulting services

12. Banco Venezolana EAP - 7 years

IBM's VSE/ESA operating system technologies project engineering and consulting services



System Software Director

SISTEMAS DE COMPUTACIÓN ABACO

May 1984 - Aug 1991 (7 years 4 months)

I was in charge of the system software products area at the North American company Computer Associates, Inc., a world leader in software development for IBM MVS, VM, and VSE operating systems.

Goal:

To provide consulting and product installation services for clients with IBM Mainframe technology.

Results:

The quality of the service provided was endorsed by my hiring by foreign entities, such as Banco Invercredito in Bogota, Colombia, and the National Registry of Costa Rica.

Projects:

1. Banco La Vivienda EAP - 1 year

VSE/ESA technical support consulting

2. Latinoamericana de Seguros - 6 months

DOS/VSE technical support consulting

3. Lagoven (a subsidiary of Venezuela's Petroleum) - 3 months

MVS technical support consulting

4. Procter & Gamble de Venezuela - 4 years

VSE/ESA management & technical support consulting

5. Interamericana de Aluminios - 3 years

VM & VSE/ESA Infrastructure & technical support consulting

6. Banco Inverbanco - 1 year

DOS/VSE technical support consulting

7. Banco Caracas - 2 months

MVS/ESA network problems resolution consulting

8. Registro Nacional de Costa Rica (overseas) - 2 weeks

MVS/ESA Problems resolution consulting

9. Ministerio de Infraestructura - 8 months

Windows Server Infrastructure consulting

10. Banco Principal - 6 months

AS/400 capacity planning consulting

11. Banco Fivenez - 4 years

DOS/VSE technical support consulting

12. Banco Hipotecario de Venezuela - 9 years

VSE/ESA technical support consulting

13. Aluminios del Caroní (Alcasa) - 3 years

VSE/ESA technical consulting

14. Banco Exterior - 6 months

VM & MVS telecommunication consulting

15. Empresa 1BC (RCTV) - 9 months

DOS/VSE technical support consulting

16. CANTV - 2 weeks

MVS network problems resolution

17. Banco Invercredito de Colombia (OVERSEA) - 1 week

VM & MVS problems resolution

System Programmer

BANCO MARACAIBO

Jan 1982 - Apr 1984 (2 years 4 months)

I was in charge of the team of specialists in the technical support division of the computing vicepresidency at the Bank.

Goal:

Among other functions, I was responsible for maintaining the operational status of the computational infrastructure based on IBM Mainframe technology.

..and finally, coordinating with other IT areas for the implementation of new projects, research, testing, and production installation (DevOps) of new versions of operating systems or software packages for both systems and applications.

stack:

- -A s/370 4381, and s/390 9021
- -IBM's VM, VSE, and MVS operating systems running on both mainframes
- -A lot of system software developed by different manufacturers
- -A SNA telecommunication network built to service a lot of bank branches
- -Interconnection links platform with other partner banks



System Programmer

BANCO NACIONAL DE DESCUENTO

Jan 1977 - Mar 1981 (4 years 3 months)

I was part of the team of specialists in the technical support division of the computing vice-presidency at the Bank.

Goal:

Like my colleagues, we were in charge of keeping the computational infrastructure based on IBM Mainframe technology operational.

Stack:

The IT and computational platform consisted of the following components:

- Two IBM 4381 mainframe technology
- IBM's VM and VSE operating systems running on both mainframe
- A lot of system software developed by several different manufacturers
- A SNA telecommunication network built to service a lot of bank branches
- Interconnection links platforms with other partner banks, and so on.

Education



🦤 Universidad Nacional Experimental Politécnica 'Antonio José de Sucre'

Ingeniero Electrónico, Mención Telecomunicaciones 1976 - 1981

Licenses & Certifications

	Z9557
	Organización y Metodos - Banco Nacional de Descuento (B.N.D)
IBM	OS/VS1 Conceptos y Facilidades - IBM
IBM	OS/VS1 JCL y Utilidades - IBM
IBM	DOS/VSE Control de Sistema - IBM L0031
IBM	DOS/VSE Conceptos y Facilidades - IBM L0030
IBM	Codificación VSAM (COBOL) - IBM
IBM	Utilización VM/CMS - IBM E7945
IBM	VM/SP Instalación - IBM E3305
	PERT C.P.M Banco de Maracaibo C.A.
IBM	CICS/VS Codificación Nivel Comando - IBM U3903
IBM	DL/1 Análisis de Aplicaciones - IBM U4302
ı	THE LIBRARIAN - Sistemas de Computación Abaco C.A. Lib-01
IBM	SNA Data Flow & Performance - IBM G3670
IBM	Capacity Planning - IBM

VM/370 Conceptos y Facilidades - IBM

L0079

MVS/JCL Utilities - IBM S3977

- ADR/DATADICTIONARY Utilización Sistemas de Computación Abaco C.A. DD-01
- English Basic I The Technical English Workshop S.A.
- SQL for DB2 & ISA for DB2 Applied Data Research (ADR an Ameritech company)
- Moving to VSE/ESA Client/Server Solutions IBM
- Tecnología de la Información y Comunicaciones La Red del Estado Universidad Nacional Experimental Fuerza Armada Nacional Centro de Investigación y Postgrado
- CICS/VSE Internals Computer Associates, Inc.
- ACF/VTAM Performance & Tuning Computer Associates, Inc.
- ACF/VTAM internals Computer Associates, Inc.
- CA-DISPATCH Internals Computer Associates, Inc.

Skills

Project Management • Project Planning • Outsourcing • Integration • Sales Management • System Deployment • Cross-functional Team Leadership • HTML & CSS developer • PHP web developer • JavaScript web developer